Introversion is an often misunderstood term.
because people relate it so much to shyness
It actually doesn't go by a "one size fits all" definition.
as it can be categorized into four different types
The four types of introverts can be vaguely described by the traits
Social
Thinking
and anxious and anxious restrained.
Social Introverts
The belief that social introverts dislike socialization is false.
Rather, they prefer to socialize in small groups of people they feel compatible with
and comfortable around.
Such as close friends or their family circle.
Thus, they're not exactly shy or reserved.
Thinking Introverts
These are people who remain introverts in their thinking process
causing them to be more thoughtful and self-reflective
For instance, they can get lost in their own dream world.
Drowned in creativity and imagination.
Anxious Introverts
Anxious introverts prefer to be alone because they feel uncomfortable or unsuitable during social gatherings
as they're not confident about their social skills.
Consequently, they are likely to choose solitude
but sometimes even solitude may not reduce their anxiety
These introverts tend to minimize anxiety by ruminating on things that could've gone wrong had they been in a particular social context.
Restrained Introverts
These are people who take time in everything they do
whether it's socializing or springing up in action.
They may seem slow since they think more carefully before they speak or act
and are more passive in nature than the active types
Now, you've probably come across an introvert in your life and labeled him or her as so, by identifying a trait that fits in one of the above types.
So, how do you know whether an introvert likes you or not?
One
Making the first move
Generally,
introverts don't make the first move in a social context.
but if you find that an introvert is actively making an effort to talk to you or making a gesture to grab your attention
you can bet he or she likes you
Two
Opening up
Introverts are not easy to crack
It takes time for them to come out of their shell and open up about themselves
However
if an introvert is telling you a lot about themselves
you are definitely someone they want to connect with
Three
Observing
As introverts are good observers, they're not quick in making friends or including people in their social circle
They take their time getting to know people and later choose them as friends
If you find that an introvert is building a good relationship with you
it means he or she wants to be close to you
Four
Inviting you into their personal space
Introverts like spending time in solitude to reflect on themselves, their thoughts and emotions
If you are invited into their personal space and asked to spend time with them
they no doubt enjoy your company
Five
Talking about personal topics
You wouldn't normally find an introvert engaging in a personal conversation
Instead
most of their conversations are generic
but if you come across an introvert that tells you about their likes and dislikes, interests, hobbies, ideologies and goals
that means they like you to the extent where they feel comfortable doing things that are considered out of character
Six
Showing extra care
Introverts place high values on relationships
They show a lot of care, concern, and empathy towards people whom they consider friends or significant others through their communications and behaviors
If an introvert is paying extra attention to you
then, they consider you as part of their close circle of friends
Seven
Going the extra mile
Introverts are very warm and helping people
If you find an introvert trying to do  things for you without you asking for help
you are someone he or she really likes
Eight
Constantly keeping in touch
Even introverts distinguish between close and personal friends
If they keep you a part of their daily lives
then you are someone special to them
Nine
Revealing secrets
Everyone has a secret they keep to themselves
Introverts especially are very careful about whom they reveal their secrets to
It can be something like allowing you to read their diary
or sharing and important aspect of their past
If an introvert is allowing you to know a secret part of their life
you are someone whom they really trust and like
Ten
Giving Feedback
Introverts don't usually give others advise or feedback
as they keep most of their opinions to themselves
but if you find that an introvert is giving you honest advise or feedback
they're definitely concerned about you and you're wellbeing.
And those are ten signs an introvert likes you
Do these traits sound like someone you know?
Do you consider yourself an introvert?
and if so, can you relate to these traits?
Let us know in the comments below
If you like this video, make sure to subscribe and check us out at our website and social media.