As one of the most notorious /nəʊˈtɔːrɪəs 臭名昭著的/ gangsters /ˈɡæŋstə 歹徒，流氓/
in history,
Al Capone presided /prɪˈzaɪd 主持/ over a vast /vɑːst/
and profitable empire of organized crime /kraɪm/.
When he was finally put on trial /ˈtraɪəl 审讯/,
the most he could be convicted /kənˈvɪkt 证明…有罪/ of
was tax evasion / ɪˈveɪʒən 逃避/.
The nearly $100 million a year,
that's 1.4 billion in today's currency,
that Capone had earned from
illegal gambling,
bootlegging /ˈbuːtˌleɡ 非法贩卖的；盗版的/,
brothels /ˈbrɒθəl 妓院/,
and extortion /ɪkˈstɔːʃən 勒索,敲诈/,
would have served as evidence
of his crimes.
But the money was nowhere
to be found.
Capone and his associates had hidden it
through investments in various businesses
whose ultimate ownership
couldn't be proven,
like cash-only laundromats /'lɔ:ndrəumæt 自助洗衣店/.
In fact, those laundromats are part of
the reason for the name of this activity,
money laundering.
Money laundering came
to be the term for any process
that cleans illegally obtained funds
of their dirty criminal origins,
allowing them to be used within
the legal economy.
But Capone wasn't the first
to launder money.
In fact, this practice is about
as old as money itself.
Merchants hid their riches from
tax collecters,
and pirates /ˈpaɪrɪt 海盗/ sought /seek/ to sell their bounty /baʊntɪ 战利品/
without drawing attention
to how they got it.
With the recent arrival
of virtual /ˈvɜːtʃuəl/ currencies,
offshore banking,
the darknet,
and global markets,
schemes have become much more complex.
Although modern money laundering
methods vary /ˈveəri 变化/ greatly,
most share three basic steps:
placement /投放/,
layering /ˈleɪə 叠加/,
and integration /ˌɪntɪˈɡreɪʃn 整合/.
Placement is where illegally obtained
money is converted into assets
that seem legitimate /lɪˈdʒɪtɪmɪt 使合法/.
That's often done by depositing funds
into a bank account
registered to an anonymous /əˈnɒnɪməs/ corporation
or a professional middleman.
This step is where criminals are often
most vulnerable to detection
since they introduce massive wealth
into the financial system
seemingly out of nowhere.
The second step, layering, involves
using multiple transactions
to further distance the funds
from their origin.
This can take the form of transfers
between multiple accounts,
or the purchase of tradable property,
like expensive cars,
artwork,
and real estate.
Casinos, where large sums of money
change hands every second,
are also popular venues for layering.
A money launderer may have their
gambling balance made available
at a casino /kəˈsiːnəʊ/ chain's locations
in other countries,
or work with employees
to rig /rɪɡ 垄断；预先做手脚 操纵/ games.
The last step, integration /ˌɪntɪˈɡreɪʃn 整合/, allows clean
money to re-enter the mainstream economy
and to benefit the original criminal.
They might invest it into a legal business
claiming payment by producing
fake /feɪk/ invoices,
or even start a bogus /ˈbəʊɡəs 伪造的 冒牌货/ charity /ˈtʃærɪtɪ/,
placing themselves
on the board of directors
with an exorbitant /ɪɡˈzɔːbɪtənt 天价的/ salary.
Money laundering itself
wasn't officially recognized as a federal
crime in the United States until 1986.
Before that point, the government
needed to prosecute /ˈprɒsɪˌkjuːt 对…提起公诉/ a related crime,
like tax evasion / ɪˈveɪʒən/.
From 1986 on, they could confiscate /ˈkɒnfɪˌskeɪt 没收，充公/
wealth simply by demonstrating
that concealment /kənˈsiːlmənt 藏匿/ had occurred,
which had a positive effect on prosecuting /ˈprɒsɪˌkjuːt 对…提起公诉/
major criminal operations,
like drug traffickers /ˈtræfɪkə 贩子/.
However, a legal shift has raised concerns
involving privacy
and government surveillance.
Today, the United Nations,
national governments,
and various nonprofits
fight against money laundering,
yet the practice continues to play
a major role in global crime.
And the most high-profile /ˈprəʊfaɪl 简介/ instances
of money laundering
have involved
not just private individuals,
but major financial institutions /ˌɪnstɪˈtjuːʃən/
and government officials.
No one knows for sure the total
amount of money
that's laundered on a yearly basis,
but some organizations estimate it to be
in the hundreds of billions of dollars.