Humans have been fascinated /ˈfæsɪˌneɪt 使着迷/
with speed for ages.
The history of human progress
is one of ever-increasing velocity,
and one of the most important achievements
in this historical race
was the breaking of the sound barrier /ˈbærɪə/.
Not long after the first
successful airplane flights,
pilots were eager to push
their planes to go faster and faster.
But as they did so, increased turbulence /ˈtɜːbjʊləns 动荡；狂暴；湍流/
and large forces on the plane
prevented them from accelerating further.
Some tried to circumvent /ˌsɜːkəmˈvɛnt 避免；绕行/
the problem through risky dives,
often with tragic results.
Finally, in 1947, design improvements,
such as a movable horizontal stabilizer /ˈsteɪbɪˌlaɪzə 水平尾翼/,
the all-moving tail,
allowed an American military pilot
named Chuck Yeager
to fly the Bell X-1 aircraft at 1127 km/h,
becoming the first person
to break the sound barrier
and travel faster than the speed of sound.
The Bell X-1 was the first of many
supersonic aircraft to follow,
with later designs reaching
speeds over Mach 3.
Aircraft traveling at supersonic speed
create a shock wave
with a thunder-like noise
known as a sonic boom,
which can cause distress /dɪˈstrɛs 忧虑，悲伤 困苦；遇难/ to people
and animals below
or even damage buildings.
For this reason,
scientists around the world
have been looking at sonic booms,
trying to predict their path
in the atmosphere,
where they will land,
and how loud they will be.
To better understand
how scientists study sonic booms,
let's start with some basics of sound.
Imagine throwing a small stone
in a still /stɪl 寂静的/ pond.
What do you see?
The stone causes waves
to travel in the water
at the same speed in every direction.
These circles that keep growing in radius /ˈreɪdɪəs 半径/
are called wave fronts.
Similarly, even though we cannot see it,
a stationary /ˈsteɪʃənərɪ 固定的；静止的/ sound source,
like a home stereo /ˈstɛrɪəʊ/,
creates sound waves traveling outward.
The speed of the waves depends on factors
like the altitude /ˈæltɪˌtjuːd 海拔/ and temperature /ˈtɛmprɪtʃə/
of the air they move through.
At sea level, sound travels
at about 1225 km/h.
But instead of circles
on a two-dimensional /daɪˈmɛnʃənəl 空间的，维的/ surface,
the wave fronts
are now concentric / kənˈsɛntrɪk 同轴的，同中心的/ spheres,
with the sound traveling along rays /reɪ 射线/
perpendicular /ˌpɜːpənˈdɪkjʊlə 垂直的，直立的/ to these waves.
Now imagine a moving sound source,
such as a train whistle.
As the source keeps moving
in a certain direction,
the successive /səkˈsɛsɪv 连续的/ waves in front of it
will become bunched closer together.
This greater wave frequency is the cause
of the famous Doppler /dɔplə/ effect,
where approaching objects
sound higher pitched /pɪtʃ 音高 投掷/.
But as long as the source is moving
slower than the sound waves themselves,
they will remain nested /ˈnestɪd 嵌套的/ within each other.
It's when an object goes supersonic,
moving faster than the sound it makes,
that the picture changes dramatically.
As it overtakes  /赶上/ sound waves
it has emitted,
while generating new ones from
its current position,
the waves are forced together,
forming a Mach cone /kəʊn 圆锥体/.
No sound is heard
as it approaches an observer
because the object is traveling faster
than the sound it produces.
Only after the object has passed
will the observer hear the sonic boom.
Where the Mach cone /kəʊn 圆锥体/ meets the ground,
it forms a hyperbola /haɪˈpɜːbələ 双曲线/,
leaving a trail /treɪl 踪迹/ known as the boom carpet /ˈkɑːpɪt 地毯/
as it travels forward.
This makes it possible to determine
the area affected by a sonic boom.
What about figuring out how strong
a sonic boom will be?
This involves solving the famous
Navier-Stokes equations /ɪˈkweɪʒən 方程式/
to find the variation /vɛərɪˈeɪʃən 变化；变异，变种/
of pressure in the air
due to the supersonic aircraft
flying through it.
This results in the pressure signature
known as the N-wave.
What does this shape mean?
Well, the sonic boom occurs
when there is a sudden change in pressure,
and the N-wave involves two booms:
one for the initial pressure rise
at the aircraft's nose,
and another for when the tail passes,
and the pressure suddenly
returns to normal.
This causes a double boom,
but it is usually heard as a single boom
by human ears.
In practice, computer models
using these principles
can often predict the location
and intensity /ɪnˈtɛnsɪtɪ 剧烈；紧张 强度/ of sonic booms
for given atmospheric conditions
and flight trajectories /trəˈdʒɛktərɪ 弹道 轨道；轨迹/,
and there is ongoing research
to mitigate /ˈmɪtɪˌɡeɪt 使减轻，缓和/ their effects.
In the meantime, supersonic flight
over land remains prohibited.
So, are sonic booms a recent creation?
Not exactly.
While we try to find ways to silence them,
a few other animals have been
using sonic booms to their advantage.
The gigantic /dʒaɪˈɡæntɪk 巨大的/ Diplodocus may have been
capable of cracking /kræk（使）爆裂；打破/ its tail
faster than sound, at over 1200 km/h,
possibly to deter /dɪˈtɜː 阻止，使不敢，使打消念头/ predators /ˈprɛdətə/.
Some types of shrimp can also create
a similar shock wave underwater,
stunning /stʌn 晕眩，猛击/ or even killing pray /preɪ 猎物；掠食/
at a distance
with just a snap /snæp   猛咬，折断/ of their oversized claw /klɔː  爪；螯，钳/.
So while we humans
have made great progress
in our relentless /rɪˈlɛntlɪs 无情的 不间断的 / pursuit of speed,
it turns out that nature was there first.