Deep inside Yale University's Beinecke
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
lies the only copy of a 240-page tome /təʊm 册,卷/.
Recently carbon dated to around 1420,
its vellum /ˈvɛləm 牛皮纸的/ pages features
looping handwriting
and hand-drawn images seemingly
stolen from a dream.
Real and imaginary plants,
floating castles,
bathing women,
astrology /əˈstrɒlədʒɪ 占星术/ diagrams /ˈdaɪəˌɡræm 图解，图表/,
zodiac /ˈzəʊdɪˌæk 黄道带/ rings,
and suns and moons with faces
accompany the text.
This 24x16 centimeter book
is called the Voynich manuscript /ˈmænjʊˌskrɪpt 手稿/,
and its one of history's biggest
unsolved mysteries /mistəriz/.
The reason why?
No one can figure out what it says.
The name comes from Wilfrid Voynich,
a Polish bookseller who came across
the document at a Jesuit college
in Italy in 1912.
He was puzzled.
Who wrote it?
Where was it made?
What do these bizarre /bɪˈzɑː 怪诞的/ words
and vibrant /ˈvaɪbrənt 振动的；响亮的；/ drawings represent?
What secrets do its pages contain?
He purchased the manuscript from
the cash-strapped /拮据/ priest /priːst 牧师/ at the college,
and eventually brought it to the U.S.,
where experts have continued to puzzle
over it for more than a century.
Cryptologists /krɪpˈtɒlədʒɪst/ say the writing has all
the characteristics /ˌkærɪktəˈrɪstɪks/ of a real language,
just one that no one's ever seen before.
What makes it seem real is that
in actual languages,
letters and groups of letters appear
with consistent frequencies,
and the language in the Voynich manuscript
has patterns you wouldn't find
from a random letter generator.
Other than that, we know little more
than what we can see.
The letters are varied
in style and height.
Some are borrowed from other scripts,
but many are unique.
The taller letters have been named
gallows /ˈɡæləʊz 绞架,绞刑/ characters.
The manuscript is
highly decorated throughout
with scroll-like embellishments /ɪmˈbelɪʃmənt 修饰，润色/.
It appears to be written by two
or more hands,
with the painting done
by yet another party.
Over the years, three main theories
about the manuscript's text have emerged.
The first is that it's written in cypher /=cipher/,
a secret code deliberately /di'libəritli 故意地；从容不迫地/ designed
to hide secret meaning.
The second is that the document is a hoax /həʊks 骗局，恶作剧/
written in gibberish /ˈdʒɪbərɪʃ  令人费解的话；胡言乱语 / to make money
off a gullible /ˈɡʌləbəl 轻信的，易受骗的/ buyer.
Some speculate /ˈspɛkjʊˌleɪt 猜测/ the author
was a medieval /ˌmɛdɪˈiːvəl 中世纪的/ con /kɒn  欺诈的/ man.
Others, that it was Voynich himself.
The third theory is that the manuscript
is written in an actual language,
but in an unknown script.
Perhaps medieval scholars were attempting
to create an alphabet /ˈælfəˌbɛt 字母表/
for a language that was spoken
but not yet written.
In that case, the Voynich manuscript
might be like the rongorongo script
invented on Easter Island,
now unreadable after the culture
that made it collapsed.
Though no one can read
the Voynich manuscript,
that hasn't stopped people from guessing
what it might say.
Those who believe the manuscript
was an attempt to create
a new form of written language
speculate that it might be an encyclopedia /ɪnˌsaɪkləˈpi:dɪə  百科全书/
containing the knowledge
of the culture that produced it.
Others believe it was written by
the 13th century philosopher /fɪˈlɒsəfə 哲学家/ Roger Bacon,
who attempted to understand
the universal laws of grammar,
or in the 16th century by the
Elizabethan mystic John Dee,
who practiced alchemy /ˈælkəmɪ 炼金术；魔力 / and divination /ˌdɪvɪˈneɪʃən 占卜,卜卦,预测/.
More fringe /frɪndʒ 刘海；穗，边缘  次要的/ theories that the book was
written by a coven /ˈkʌvən 女巫大聚会/ of Italian witches,
or even by Martians /ˈmɑːʃən 火星人/.
After 100 years of frustration /frʌˈstreɪʃən 挫败/,
scientists have recently shed /ʃɛd 使泄出；流血；/ a little
light on the mystery.
The first breakthrough
was the carbon dating.
Also, contemporary /kənˈtɛmprərɪ 同一时代的/ historians /hɪˈstɔːrɪən/ have
traced the provenance /ˈprɒvɪnəns 起源,出处/ of the manuscript
back through Rome and Prague /prɑːɡ 布拉格/
to as early as 1612,
when it was perhaps passed
from Holy Roman Emperor Rudolf II
to his physician /fɪˈzɪʃən 内科医生/, Jacobus Sinapius.
In addition to these
historical breakthroughs,
linguistic researchers recently proposed
the provisional /prəˈvɪʒənəl 暂时的/ identification
of a few of the manuscript's words.
Could the letters beside these seven
stars spell Tauran,
a name for Taurus,
a constellation /ˌkɒnstɪˈleɪʃən 星座 / that includes the seven
stars called the Pleiades?
Could this word be Centaurun
for the Centaurea plant in the picture?
Perhaps, but progress is slow.
If we can crack its code,
what might we find?
The dream journal of
a 15th-century illustrator /ˈɪləˌstreɪtə/?
A bunch of nonsense /ˈnɒnsəns/?
Or the lost knowledge
of a forgotten culture?
What do you think it is?