It's not hard to imagine a world
where at any given moment,
you and everyone you know could be
wiped /waɪp/ out without warning
at the push of a button.
This was the reality for millions
of people during the 45-year period
after World War II,
now known as the Cold War.
As the United States and Soviet /ˈsəʊvɪət/ Union
faced off across the globe,
each knew that the other had nuclear
weapons capable /ˈkeɪpəbəl/ of destroying it.
And destruction never loomed /luːm 朦胧/ closer
than during the 13 days
of the Cuban /ˈkjuːbən/ Missile Crisis.
In 1961, the U.S. unsuccessfully tried to
overthrow /ˌəʊvəˈθrəʊ 推翻/ Cuba's /ˈkjuːbə/ new communist /ˈkɒmjʊnɪst/ government.
That failed attempt was known
as the Bay of Pigs,
and it convinced /kənˈvɪnst 确信/ Cuba to seek help
from the U.S.S.R.
Soviet premier /ˈprɛmjə 总理/ Nikita Khrushchev /kruːsˈtʃɒf/
was happy to comply /kəmˈplaɪ 服从/
by secretly deploying nuclear
missiles to Cuba,
not only to protect the island,
but to counteract /ˌkaʊntərˈækt 抵消/ the threat from
U.S. missiles in Italy /ˈɪtəlɪ/ and Turkey.
By the time U.S. intelligence
discovered the plan,
the materials to create the missiles
were already in place.
At an emergency meeting on
October 16, 1962,
military advisors urged an airstrike
on missile sites
and invasion /ɪnˈveɪʒən/ of the island.
But President John F. Kennedy /ˈkenɪdɪ/ chose
a more careful approach.
On October 22, he announced that the
the U.S. Navy
would intercept all shipments to Cuba.
There was just one problem:
a naval blockade /blɒˈkeɪd （尤指对港口的）封锁/ was considered
an act of war.
Although the President called it
a quarantine /ˈkwɒrənˌtiːn 检疫，隔离/
that did not block basic necessities /nəˈsesɪtɪz/,
the Soviets didn't appreciate
the distinction /dɪˈstɪŋkʃən 差异/.
In an outraged /ˈaʊtˌreɪdʒ 愤怒/ letter to Kennedy,
Khrushchev wrote, "The violation
of freedom to use international waters
and international airspace
is an act of aggression /əˈɡreʃən 侵犯 /
which pushes mankind toward the abyss /əˈbɪs 深渊/
of world nuclear missile war."
Thus ensued /ɪnˈsjuː 接着发生/ the most intense
six days of the Cold War.
While the U.S. demanded the removal /rɪˈmuːvəl/
of the missiles,
Cuba and the U.S.S.R insisted
they were only defensive.
And as the weapons continued
to be armed,
the U.S. prepared for a possible invasion.
On October 27, a spy plane piloted
by Major Rudolph Anderson
was shot down by a Soviet missile.
The same day, a nuclear-armed Soviet
submarine /ˈsʌbməˌriːn/ was hit by a small-depth charge
from a U.S. Navy vessel /ˈvɛsəl 船 血管 / trying
to signal /ˈsɪɡnəl/ it to come up.
The commanders on the sub,
too deep to communicate with the surface /ˈsɜːfɪs/,
thought war had begun
and prepared to launch a nuclear torpedo /tɔːˈpiːdəʊ/.
That decision had to be made unanimously /juːˈnænɪməslɪ/
by three officers.
The captain and political officer
both authorized the launch,
but Vasili Arkhipov,
second in command, refused.
His decision saved the day
and perhaps the world.
But the crisis wasn't over.
For the first time in history,
the U.S. Military set itself
to DEFCON 2,
the defense readiness one step
away from nuclear war.
With hundreds of nuclear missiles
ready to launch,
the metaphorical /ˌmetəˈfɒrɪkəl 隐喻的/ Doomsday Clock
stood at one minute to midnight.
But diplomacy /dɪˈpləʊməsɪ/ carried on.
In Washington /ˈwɒʃɪŋtən/, D.C., Attorney General
Robert Kennedy
secretly met with Soviet Ambassador /æmˈbæsədə/
Anatoly Dobrynin.
After intense negotiation,
they reached the following proposal.
The U.S. would remove their missiles
from Turkey and Italy
and promise to never invade Cuba
in exchange for the Soviet withdrawal
from Cuba under U.N. inspection.
Once the meeting had concluded,
Dobrynin cabled /ˈkeɪbəl （给...）发电报/ Moscow /ˈmɒskəʊ/ saying
time is of the essence /ˈɛsəns 本质/
and we shouldn't miss the chance.
And at 9 a.m. the next day,
a message arrived from Khrushchev
announcing the Soviet missiles would be
removed from Cuba.
The crisis was now over.
While criticized /ˈkrɪtɪˌsaɪz/ at the time by their
respective /rɪˈspɛktɪv 各自的/ governments
for bargaining with the enemy,
contemporary /kənˈtɛmprərɪ 同代人/ historical /hɪˈstɒrɪkəl/ analysis
shows great admiration /ˌædməˈreɪʃən 赞美/
for Kennedy's and Khrushchev's ability
to diplomatically /ˌdɪpləˈmætɪkəlɪ/ solve the crisis.
But the disturbing /dɪˈstɜːb 打扰/ lesson was that
a slight communication error,
or split-second decision by a commander,
could have thwarted /θwɔːt 阻挠，挫败/ all their efforts,
as it nearly did if not for
Vasili Arkhipov's courageous /kəˈreɪdʒəs/ choice.
The Cuban Missile Crisis revealed just how
fragile /ˈfrædʒaɪl/ human politics are
compared to the terrifying power
they can unleash /ʌnˈliːʃ 解除...的束缚/.