Have you experienced déjà vu?
It's that shadowy /ˈʃædəʊɪ 朦胧的/ feeling you get
when a situation seems familiar.
A scene in a restaurant plays out
exactly as you remember.
The world moves like a ballet /ˈbæleɪ/
you've choreographed /ˈkɒrɪəˌɡrɑːf 编舞/,
but the sequence can't be based
on a past experience
because you've never eaten here before.
This is the first time you've had clams /klæm 蛤/,
so what's going on?
Unfortunately, there isn't
one single explanation /ˌɛkspləˈneɪʃən/ for déjà vu.
The experience is brief
and occurs without notice,
making it nearly impossible
for scientists to record and study it.
Scientists can't simply sit around
and wait for it to happen to them --
this could take years.
It has no physical manifestations /ˌmænɪfeˈsteɪʃən 迹象/
and in studies,
it's described by the subject
as a sensation /sɛnˈseɪʃən 知觉/ or feeling.
Because of this lack of hard evidence,
there's been a surplus /ˈsɜrˌplʌs 过剩的/
of speculation /ˌspɛkjʊˈleɪʃən 推测/ over the years.
Since Emile Boirac introduced déjà vu
as a French term meaning "already seen,"
more than 40 theories attempt
to explain this phenomenon.
Still, recent advancements in neuroimaging
and cognitive /ˈkɒɡnɪtɪv 认识的/ psychology
narrow down the field of prospects /prɔspekt 预期/.
Let's walk through three of today's
more prevalent /ˈprɛvələnt 流行的/ theories,
using the same
restaurant setting for each.
First up is dual /ˈdjuːəl 双数/ processing.
We'll need an action.
Let's go with a waiter
dropping a tray /treɪ 托盘/ of dishes.
As the scene unfolds,
your brain's hemispheres process
a flurry /ˈflɜri 慌张 一阵风/ of information:
the waiter's flailing arms,
his cry for help,
the smell of pasta /ˈpæstə/.
Within milliseconds, this information
zips through pathways
and is processed into a single moment.
Most of the time,
everything is recorded in-sync /sɪŋk 同步/.
However, this theory asserts /əˈsə:t 断言/
that déjà vu occurs
when there's a slight delay
in information from one of these pathways.
The difference in arrival times
causes the brain to interpret /ɪnˈtɜːprɪt 解释/
the late information
as a separate event.
When it plays
over the already-recorded moment,
it feels as if it's happened before
because, in a sense, it has.
Our next theory deals
with a confusion of the past
rather than a mistake in the present /ˈprɛzənt/.
This is the hologram /ˈhɒləˌɡræm 全息图/ theory,
and we'll use that tablecloth /ˈteɪbəlklɒθ/
to examine it.
As you scan its squares,
a distant memory swims up
from deep within your brain.
According to the theory,
this is because memories are stored
in the form of holograms /ˈhɒləˌɡræm 全息图/,
and in holograms,
you only need one fragment
to see the whole picture.
Your brain has identified the tablecloth
with one from the past,
maybe from your grandmother's house.
However, instead of remembering
that you've seen it at your grandmother's,
your brain has summoned /ˈsʌmən 召见/ up the old memory
without identifying it.
This leaves you stuck /stʌk 陷入/ with familiarity,
but no recollection.
Although you've never been
in this restaurant,
you've seen that tablecloth
but are just failing to identify it.
Now, look at this fork.
Are you paying attention?
Our last theory is divided attention,
and it states /steɪt 陈述/ that déjà vu occurs
when our brain subliminally /sʌbˈlɪmɪnəlɪ 潜在意识地/
takes in an environment
while we're distracted /dɪˈstræktɪd 思想不集中的/
by one particular object.
When our attention returns,
we feel as if we've been here before.
For example, just now
you focused on the fork
and didn't observe the tablecloth
or the falling waiter.
Although your brain has been
recording everything
in your peripheral /pəˈrɪfərəl 次要的/ vision,
it's been doing so
below conscious awareness.
When you finally pull yourself
away from the fork,
you think you've been here before
because you have,
you just weren't paying attention.
While all three of these theories
share the common features of déjà vu,
none of them propose /prəˈpəʊz 提议/ to be
the conclusive /kənˈkluːsɪv 决定性的/ source
of the phenomenon.
Still, while we wait
for researchers and inventers /inˈventə 发明家/
to come up with new ways
to capture this fleeting /fliːt 转瞬即逝的 / moment,
we can study the moment ourselves.
After all, most studies of déjà vu
are based on first-hand accounts,
so why can't one be yours?
The next time you get déjà vu,
take a moment to think about it.
Have you been distracted?
Is there a familiar object somewhere?
Is your brain just acting slow?
Or is it something else?