What is imposter /ɪmˈpɒstə 冒名顶替者/ syndrome /ˈsɪndrəʊm 并发症/ and how can you combat it
Even after writing eleven books
and winning several prestigious /preˈstɪdʒəs 享有声望的，声望很高的/ awards,
Maya Angelou couldn’t escape
the nagging /næg 唠叨 不停地抱怨/ doubt
that she hadn’t really earned
her accomplishments.
Albert Einstein /ˈaɪnstaɪn/ experienced
something similar:
he described himself
as an “involuntary /ɪnˈvɒləntərɪ 自然而然的,无意识的/ swindler /ˈswɪndlə 骗子/”
whose work didn’t deserve
as much attention as it had received.
Accomplishments at the level
of Angelou’s or Einstein’s are rare,
but their feeling of fraudulence /ˈfrɔːdjʊləns 欺诈/
is extremely common.
Why can’t so many of us shake feelings
that we haven’t earned
our accomplishments,
or that our ideas and skills
aren’t worthy of others’ attention?
Psychologist Pauline Rose Clance
was the first to study
this unwarranted sense of insecurity.
In her work as a therapist,
she noticed many of her undergraduate
patients shared a concern:
though they had high grades,
they didn’t believe they deserved
their spots at the university.
Some even believed their acceptance
had been an admissions error.
While Clance knew these fears
were unfounded /ʌnˈfaʊndɪd 无根据的/,
she could also remember feeling
the exact /ɪɡˈzækt 精确的/ same way in graduate school.
She and her patients experienced
something that goes by a number of names--
imposter imposter /ɪmˈpɒstə 冒名顶替者/ phenomenon,
imposter experience,
and imposter syndrome /ˈsɪndrəʊm 并发症/.
Together with colleague /ˈkɒliːɡ/ Suzanne Imes,
Clance first studied imposterism
in female college students and faculty.
Their work established pervasive /pɜːˈveɪsɪv 弥漫的；渗透的 普遍的；/
feelings of fraudulence /ˈfrɔːdjʊləns 欺诈/ in this group.
Since that first study,
the same thing has been established
across gender,
race,
age,
and a huge range of occupations,
though it may be more prevalent /ˈprɛvələnt 流行的/
and disproportionately /ˌdɪsprəˈpɔːʃənɪtlɪ  不成比例地/ affect
the experiences of underrepresented /ˌʌndəˌreprɪˈzentɪd  未被充分代表的/
or disadvantaged groups.
To call it a syndrome /ˈsɪndrəʊm 并发症/
is to downplay /ˈdaʊnˌpleɪ 对…轻描淡写；轻视/ how universal /ˌjuːnɪˈvɜːsəl 广泛适用的/ it is.
It's not a disease or an abnormality /ˌæbnɔːˈmælɪtɪ 不正常/,
and it isn’t necessarily
tied to depression,
anxiety,
or self-esteem /ɪˈstiːm 敬重/.
Where do these feelings
of fraudulence come from?
People who are highly skilled
or accomplished
tend to think others are just as skilled.
This can spiral /ˈspaɪərəl 螺旋/ into feelings
that they don’t deserve accolades /ˈækəˌleɪd 嘉奖；荣誉/
and opportunities over other people.
And as Angelou and Einstein experienced,
there’s often no threshold /ˈθrɛʃəʊld 极限；临界值/
of accomplishment
that puts these feelings to rest.
Feelings of imposterism aren’t restricted
to highly skilled individuals, either.
Everyone is susceptible /səˈsɛptɪbəl 易受影响的；易感动的/ to a phenomenon
known as pluralistic /ˌplʊərəˈlɪstɪk 兼职的,多元论的/  ignorance /ˈɪɡnərəns 无知，愚昧/,
where we each doubt ourselves privately,
but believe we’re alone
in thinking that way
because no one else voices their doubts.
Since it’s tough /tʌf 棘手的/ to really know
how hard our peers /pɪə 凝视 同事 同辈/ work,
how difficult they find certain tasks,
or how much they doubt themselves,
there’s no easy way to dismiss feelings
that we’re less capable
than the people around us.
Intense feelings of imposterism
can prevent people
from sharing their great ideas
or applying for jobs
and programs where they’d excel /ɪkˈsɛl 胜过，优于；擅长/.
At least so far,
the most surefire /ʃuəfaiə 准不会有错的，确实的，可靠的/ way
to combat imposter syndrome
is to talk about it.
Many people suffering
from imposter syndrome
are afraid that if they ask
about their performance,
their fears will be confirmed.
And even when
they receive positive feedback,
it often fails /feɪl/ to ease
feelings of fraudulence.
But on the other hand,
hearing that an advisor or mentor /ˈmɛntɔː 指导者，导师 指导/ has
experienced feelings of imposterism
can help relieve those feelings.
The same goes for peers.
Even simply finding out there’s a term /项/
for these feelings
can be an incredible relief.
Once you’re aware of the phenomenon,
you can combat /ˈkɒmbæt/ your own imposter syndrome
by collecting
and revisiting positive feedback.
One scientist who kept blaming herself
for problems in her lab
started to document the causes
every time something went wrong.
Eventually, she realized most
of the problems
came from equipment failure,
and came to recognize her own competence /ˈkɒmpɪtəns 能力；权限/.
We may never be able
to banish /ˈbænɪʃ 驱逐；消除/ these feelings entirely,
but we can have open conversations
about academic /ækə'demɪk/ or professional challenges.
With increasing awareness
of how common /ˈkɒmən/ these experiences are,
perhaps we can feel freer to be frank  /fræŋk 直率的/
about our feelings
and build confidence
in some simple truths:
you have talent,
you are capable,
and you belong /适宜/.