When we talk about English,
we often think of it as a single language
but what do the dialects /ˈdaɪəˌlɛkt 方言；土语；地方话/ spoken
in dozens of countries around the world
have in common with each other,
or with the writings of Chaucer?
And how are any of them related
to the strange words in Beowulf?
The answer is that like most languages,
English has evolved  /ɪˈvɒlv 发展；进化/
through generations of speakers,
undergoing major /ˈmeɪdʒə/ changes over time.
By undoing these changes,
we can trace the language
from the present /ˈprɛzənt/ day
back to its ancient /ˈeɪnʃənt/ roots.
While modern English
shares many similar words
with /ˈlætɪn/ Latin-derived /dɪˈraɪvd 衍生的/ romance /rəuˈmæns/ languages,
like French and Spanish,
most of those words
were not originally part of it.
Instead, they started coming
into the language
with the Norman /ˈnɔːmən 诺曼第人/ invasion
of England in 1066.
When the French-speaking Normans
conquered /ˈkɒŋkə/ England
and became its ruling class,
they brought their speech with them,
adding a massive /ˈmæsɪv 大规模的/ amount
of French and Latin vocabulary
to the English language
previously /ˈpriːvɪəslɪ 先前地/ spoken there.
Today, we call that language Old English.
This is the language of Beowulf.
It probably doesn't look very familiar,
but it might be more recognizable
if you know some German.
That's because Old English
belongs to the Germanic language family,
first brought to the British Isles /aɪl 岛/
in the 5th and 6th centuries
by the Angles, Saxons, and Jutes.
The Germanic dialects they spoke would
become known as Anglo-Saxon.
Viking /ˈvaɪkɪŋ/ invaders in the 8th
to 11th centuries
added more borrowings
from Old Norse into the mix.
It may be hard to see the roots
of modern English
underneath all the words borrowed
from French, Latin, Old Norse
and other languages.
But comparative /kəmˈpærətɪv 比较的/ linguistics /lɪŋˈɡwɪstɪks 语言学/ can help us
by focusing on grammatical /ɡrəˈmætɪkəl 语法的/ structure,
patterns of sound changes,
and certain core vocabulary.
For example, after the 6th century,
German words starting with "p,"
systematically /ˌsɪstəˈmætɪklɪ 系统地，有计划地/ shifted to a "pf" sound
while their Old English counterparts
kept the "p" unchanged.
In another split, words
that have "sk" sounds in Swedish /ˈswiːdɪʃ 瑞典语/
developed an "sh" sound in English.
There are still some English
words with "sk,"
like "skirt," and "skull,"  /skʌl 头骨/
but they're direct borrowings
from Old Norse
that came after the "sk" to "sh" shift.
These examples show us
that just as the various Romance languages
descended /dɪˈsendɪd 的后裔/ from Latin,
English, Swedish, German,
and many other languages
descended from their own common ancestor /ˈænsɛstə 祖先/
known as Proto-Germanic
spoken around 500 B.C.E.
Because this historical language
was never written down,
we can only reconstruct it
by comparing its descendants,
which is possible thanks
to the consistency /kənˈsɪstənsɪ 连贯性/ of the changes.
We can even use the same process
to go back one step further,
and trace the origins of Proto-Germanic
to a language called Proto-Indo-European,
spoken about 6000 years ago
on the Pontic steppe  /step 西伯利亚一带没有树木的大草原/
in modern day Ukraine /juːˈkreɪn/ and Russia.
This is the reconstructed ancestor /ˈænsɛstə 祖先/
of the Indo-European family
that includes nearly all languages
historically spoken in Europe,
as well as large parts of Southern
and Western Asia.
And though it requires a bit more work,
we can find the same systematic
similarities /ˌsɪmɪˈlærɪtɪ 相似之处/, or correspondences /ˌkɒrɪˈspɒndəns 信函 一致/,
between related words in different
Indo-European branches.
Comparing English with Latin,
we see that English has "t"
where Latin has "d",
and "f" where latin has "p"
at the start of words.
Some of English's more distant relatives
include Hindi, Persian /ˈpɜːʃən 波斯人/
and the Celtic languages it displaced /dɪsˈpleɪs 替换/
in what is now Britain.
Proto-Indo-European itself descended
from an even more ancient /ˈeɪnʃənt/ language,
but unfortunately, this is as far back
as historical /hɪˈstɒrɪkəl/ and archeological /ˌɑːkɪəˈlɒdʒɪkəl 考古学的/ evidence
will allow us to go.
Many mysteries /ˈmɪstərɪ 神秘/ remain just out of reach,
such as whether there might be a link
between Indo-European
and other major language families,
and the nature of the languages spoken
in Europe prior /ˈpraɪə 优先的/ to its arrival.
But the amazing fact remains that nearly
3 billion people around the world,
many of whom cannot understand each other,
are nevertheless /ˌnɛvəðəˈlɛs 然而/ speaking the same words
shaped by 6000 years of history.